Okay. Can everyone see my screen?
Or can anyone see my screen and hear
me?
Just give me a thumbs up. Okay, I got one from Ron.
Excellent. Okay. So,
any questions from last time from anyone who's online?
I know I've gotten several
emails about problems one and two,
and I am working on getting through those. I got a lot of emails on that.
So,
I think we went over that last week, though.
So, you might be wondering why I stuck bioastronautics
in between the space satellite environmental topics.
And the reason is I'm teaching a ground class
that is basically the same as this.
It's in a combined undergraduate-graduate class.
And I needed a sub this week because I just had surgery last
Wednesday,
and this is the topic my sub was most familiar
with. So, I'm doing this to align with my ground class
at UCCS.
So to start off,
I just want to say that next week, we will be going back
to the space environment and the effects on spacecraft,
and that will be involving the plasma environment.
So make sure you read ahead on that once I post the material,
and bring your questions. So to start off with, and I'm looking
for audience participation on this
via chat,
where should humans be in 2040?
Your answer may be the Earth
or the bottom of the ocean, but
should we be anywhere in our solar system by
other than just here on the Earth?
Any thoughts on that?
You can just put your comments in the chat.
"Mars or Moon," Jordan says. Great.
Hopefully we're in the process of putting humans on the moon, but maybe
onto Mars, which is a completely different challenge.
Yeah. Mars or the Moon.
Anyone else have any other thoughts?
Okay. So,
my first two choices were the Moon, Mars.
The Moon and Mars.
But
excuse me. NASA
actually asked us to look into a human
mission to the dwarf planet, Ceres, about...
Let's see, that's been about five years ago.
So, going beyond Mars is definitely on their radar
screen. So we participated in a competition called
Rascal, and Rascal is looking at where NASA
is looking at going in
the future in 10, 20 years,
and that was on their radar screen.
So we'll look at some features of Ceres tonight.
Or should we be out as far as Titan? You've heard about Saturn's moon,
Titan. It has a lot of intriguing features,
and maybe putting humans on there would be within our reach,
or probably not one of Jupiter's moons.
There's way too much radiation.
Saturn will have a good bit of radiation, but not as much as
Jupiter. So,
those are some thoughts along those lines.
Yeah, Jordan?
Yeah, so I was having a chat with a colleague one
time, and he was talking about some work that his brother had
done on stable areas in
between transfer routes, like in between orbits, essentially.
And how there may be some-
You mean Lagrange points?
Yes.
Okay.
And having stationary stations in
between there for refueling or resupplying type stuff.
Oh, yeah.
I don't know if that's something that we'd
had heard much about or not, but just a kind of a curiosity since you had brought
up this topic.
Yeah. That's a great thought. We looked,
I think it was 2022. I had a group
of students look into a resupply
platform at Earth-Moon L1.
And the idea was that you could put the platform there, and
other satellites could come up to it and refuel
or replace parts, although that was a bigger task than
we thought. But yeah, that's definitely something
that has been looked into. There's a lot of papers out there.
I've got one of them out there
you could
feel free to look at. It's called the L1 Resupply
Platform at L1,
and it was presented at the
AIAA
Ascend
Conference, I think in 2022. But I
will
make a note-
Awesome. I'll look for that.
Yeah. I will make a note to post
That paper, it's on my ResearchGate. I'll just post a link.
Post
paper
on L1 platform.
Yeah, and it garnered a lot of interest when we presented it at the conference.
So, mm-hmm.
Okay. So first up, we have our
current events presentation, and these are
via video. Now notice
that homework problem number one on homework
three
is to summarize these two presentations.
Describe something you learned from it and write one question you have
left about the presentation. And the
idea is that I would look into some of
those questions, possibly collaborate with the
presenters, and then we would talk about
lessons learned from the previous week's
presentations
once I get those homeworks in. So we'll start with
Shelby Schreckenberg,
and you'll have to tell me, I think I'm going to have to
share my new screen
here. So
let me see. Share.
There we go.
Is it open?
I know I have it open.
Give
me just a moment while I figure out some technical
difficulties that always comes with
the first lesson.
I think this is it. Yep. This is it. Okay.
First off, let's test it.
My name is Shelby Schreckenberg.
Could you all hear that and see the slides?
Yep. I can hear it and see it.
Okay, good. All right. So if you just
write down the answers to those three questions on this
video, you'll have homework problem one done.
And this is my presentation on bioastronautics.
You'll have homework problem one done. Here it is.
Excellent. So we're going to go over today kind of what it
is, the importance of this topic, and the research of it,
all the different kinds of medical issues that we see that come with
bioastronautics, as well as treatment and the safe practices, and
what's coming next.
So what is bioastronautics? Bioastronautics is the biological study of
how life is and acts in outer space.
This is a combination of the study of biology and astrodynamics.
It involves a safe flight. Obviously, we want our humans to get to space
safely, so seeing how that impacts a human
body, as well as living conditions in space, just how our bodies
react to a no-gravity environment,
as well as life support conditions while living in space and coming
back to Earth post your time in space.
It became a big area of research after the Apollo 11 mission,
and all of NASA's information about it actually comes from the Space
Medicine and Healthcare Systems office.
They define the medical standards for how NASA sends their astronauts into space
and what they provide.
Why is it important? Space is constantly wanting to be explored by humans, so
we have to find a way to make sure that they can stay healthy and safe while they
are in space. We don't want to have any of our astronauts to have
issues. It is to make sure the environment that the humans are in up there in
a zero-gravity environment are livable, and that this
environment can sustain them for however long that they are needed to be up
there. As well as how space impacts their health
and the wellness of their bodies, and to reduce any medical
issues that can occur in space or the flight or the return.
So we see that bioastronautics is used to research medical issues
that can come up in space and the prevention of them as well.
These medical issues can occur at a number of ways,
but it mainly is at the anatomical, biochemical, or
physiological level. So pretty much anything in your body.
Some medical issues that can occur, and these are not all of them, is bone
density loss, that's similar to osteoporosis here on Earth,
muscle loss or atrophy,
fluid shift causing puffiness, nasal congestion, and more.
This occurs from your blood not necessarily flowing the exact
speed or way that it should be from being in a zero-gravity
environment. Physiological shifts just in the body, heart
conditions as well from the
movement of your blood, as well as decreased immune system.
You are quarantined before you even go to space, and you're around the same
people with limited and hardly to none, no
access of bacteria like we are here on Earth.
So coming back to Earth, your immune system can be significantly lowered, as
well as radiation sicknesses. We have seen in
this class that the sun and its
weather can cause radiation to occur and just
how that affects humans, because that's not a good thing to
have.
We also see that motion sickness usually occurs the first few days in space.
This makes a lot of sense. You're on a constant move compared to most
of us sit at a desk most of the day while we are
here.
On Earth. And then usually after a few days, they can start to adapt to this
environment.
But also just zero gravity affects organs and their functions.
We are born into gravity. Our bodies know how to react in gravity.
So when we are put in an environment that does not have that, you can
have numerous issues on any organ that's in your
body and just how they react to that.
We also see that a return to gravity can cause issues with balance,
function of different muscles or parts of your body, and the
orientation. You're coming from one environment, being up
there and getting used to it, and having to completely get used to gravity again.
We see that posture, walking, and disorientation can occur upon returning to
Earth. It usually will resolve itself within a few days to
a week or a few weeks, depending on the time in space.
So obviously the longer that you are in space, the more pronounced the
symptoms and the issues are going to be and the longer that it is going to
take for all of those to reside.
So how we see that it is treated. First off, you see workouts in space.
You can see from the photo here, that is a machine that is
used to help try and use your muscles so you're not completely
losing all of them while up in space.
We also see they have bicycles and all kinds of other
ways to build up that muscle or just to keep it
used and
that
you are keeping track of your body.
We also see ultrasounds and MRIs on the ISS.
It is very hard to find people who are trained in that,
but usually,
some people know a general amount of this and are able to perform those as
absolutely necessary. They have those machines on the ISS, so if
something needs to happen, they can do those and send that back to
Earth. We also see light therapy for circadian rhythm.
We know that there are many different light colors that can help the
human body naturally to fall asleep.
There's no night and day in space compared to here on
Earth. And at night, we see a lot of those red and orange
lights from the sun to help our body naturally wind down.
And so having those to help our body create a natural melatonin is
great, but there is melatonin and other sleep aids that are
given upon the ISS just to help, because when
you have very limited sleep or no sleep, you obviously are not going to perform to
the level that you could. We also see benzodiazepines.
These are kind of like an antidepressant, but they're prescribed to
treat conditions such as anxiety,
insomnia, and seizures. Any of these can happen and occur
upon the ISS or just while in space on a mission.
So having those can help to decrease
those issues that could happen while there.
We also see mitigating radiation exposure.
As we said before, the sun can give off a lot.
So there's many different radiation sensors aboard the ISS
that depending on the level
of your orbit, it will have different amounts of
times that they go off, and they will constantly be checking how much
radiation is coming onto the ISS that could also be affecting
humans.
So we also know that there's got to be safe practices while on
the ISS or while on a mission, and so we need clean air
processes, just ways to recycle our air
and put oxygen back into it, because we obviously need that to
breathe, as well as clean water, and that comes with processing waste
products while on the ISS or again,
any mission. We see the photo to the right kind of just
shows a general idea on how they recycle and treat that
water in order to consume that again.
We also want all of our astronauts to have healthy nutritional food.
You're going to need all that stuff for when you come back to Earth, and you're
trying to build your body back up. We don't want you missing out on
any sort of vitamin or nutrient that could be detrimental
to your body. As well as disease and health management prevention.
Again, we have seen that there's an MRIs
and ultrasounds as well as different medications
aboard the ISS, and this is just a way to prevent
anything serious from happening or to
prevent any reason that they would need to be sent back home
sooner than expected.
What's next? So we want to continue this research for ways to help humans in space.
We still see a lot of issues for when people come back after being
up there for a prolonged amount of time.
And so being able to take this information from when humans are in
space and have them document what's going on, what they
could expect, what they would need more for next time, can help to
increase the amount of things and availability that we
can give to these astronauts while on a
mission in order to make their environment
healthier and easier and more sustainable. We want adaptability research.
Again, just how our bodies can adapt to that in a better way.
What things we could do, whether here on Earth or when we
first go on our mission, in order to help our bodies adapt
from a gravity to a no-gravity environment, and ways to increase the
capability of longer space flights.
We see with our missions that we are constantly wanting to go further than
just orbiting the Earth. So that obviously takes a longer
mission to do, and in order to do that, we need to understand how
human bodies will be affected on a longer space
flight or mission. And having that knowledge and research is a good
way to help prevent any medical issues from
occurring.
And that is all I have. Thank you for your time.
Have a good day.
Okay, so that was our first
presentation of the semester, or of the term.
It was broadly covered a lot of different topics.
The next one is very specific, but I did want to point out one
thing.
As far as long-duration human flight,
I have some students working on a project right now to
determine how much radiation and
mitigation we'd be able to provide, or
mitigation strategies, for a human series mission.
So again, following up on the NASA concept.
And the reason that came up is we proposed a mission to
Ceres at a conference by going by
Mars first, using a gravity assist.
And the judges where we were presenting said
there's no way anyone could survive getting to
Ceres
because it's too long and you'd be exposed to too much radiation.
And that wasn't really the topic of our paper.
Our
topic of the paper was the astrodynamics in
getting there.
But when you get feedback like that at a conference, it's
something to look into. So I currently
have some students working on modeling the radiation
environment and determining some mitigation strategies
to a mission to Ceres.
Okay. The second one
is very much more
specific.
And let me share this one.
So today I'm going to be-
So let me know if you can't hear or see it.
I'll assume you can otherwise
... talking about AVATAR, which is a Virtual Astronaut Tissue
Analog Response experiment aboard Artemis II.
This is a presentation by me, Grace Burns.
Thank you for listening.
So in summary, AVATAR is an experiment, like I
mentioned, aboard Artemis II that utilizes
organ-on-a-chip technology.
We will get more into that later. So the goal of this experiment is to
understand how radiation and microgravity affect human tissues
long term, and this
knowledge will be leveraged for Moon and Mars missions,
deep space exploration, things like that.
This does support research into preventative measures to
help ensure the long-term health
of our astronauts.
And additionally, this informs on individual needs because this
organ-on-a-chip technology is individual specific, so we'll be
able to tell what kind of extra needs each specific astronaut
has.
So how it works is that for each thing they're emulating, there are
two identical chips. One stays here on Earth and the other
goes aboard the Artemis II mission.
Post-mission, these two different chips will be compared for DNA
damage, cell growth, immune responses, and radiation effects.
And this kind of experiment is innovative because it doesn't have
invasive testing on the astronauts, and it's more accurate than lab
results since these tissues are actually going into
space, and that cannot be replicated in any kind of lab, at least not
perfectly.
Now, this experiment is not without validation.
How they're going to validate it is to compare pre- and
post-mission blood samples from each of the astronauts.
All right. So on the left here you can see a picture of one of these organ chips.
It's very tiny. It's a USB drive size.
So in these chips, bone marrow is used since bone marrow contains
stem cells that can be formed into red blood cells, white blood cells and
platelets, among other things.
So these organ chips mimic organs like the heart, the brain, the
liver, et cetera.
And also because it can form into white blood cells, it can
mimic immune responses.
All right. So it's very interesting.
I wanted to talk about how the samples are obtained
because I went into kind of a deep dive about this specifically, but
the astronauts are supposed to go to a
local health clinic and donate platelets,
and then that donation is sent off and what is left of the sample that they're
donating contains small amounts of the stem cells
that are derived from the bone marrow.
And then Emulate, which is the company that's
developing these organ chips,
their scientists process the cells from this
leftover donation
using magnetic beads. And these beads bind
specifically to the type of cells, the stem cells that they're looking for.
And then using the magnets, these cells are placed into the bone marrow
chips.
So then each chip is connected using blood vessel cells
and supporting structures to model
the specific function they're trying to emulate.
For example, if they're trying to emulate a heart, they'll add the structure that
the heart needs around it.
And then this type of system is then mounted together
in the payload, which is an automated, self-contained system.
It's battery-powered. It's totally
independent of the rest of the payloads aboard Artemis II.
And you can see a picture of that whole system on the right here.
It is being developed by Space Tango.
So, very interesting. The projected
results of this experiment are that we can understand specific astronaut
needs to inform anything that they're bringing on board
health-wise.
And then also, hopefully, we'll find out how to keep
astronauts nice and healthy for longer so that it can allow for
deeper space exploration.
Then a secondary mission for this technology, not a
super
main one, but this can be used to test
pharmaceuticals.
Benefits these kind of researchers on Earth as well.
So thank you everybody for listening to my presentation.
If you have any questions please put it in homework three.
And I'd like to shout out Slidesgo, because this is a template by them and
it made my presentation a lot cuter.
So thank you so much, Slidesgo, and thank you guys for listening.
Okay, so that one was about a specific technology,
and what's particularly exciting is that
it was applied on Artemis II.
So
I assume we will be getting some
results back from that here
pretty soon.
Let me go back to slideshow.
Why is it not going to slideshow?
There we go. Can y'all see my slides again?
Thumbs up, yeah, thumbs down, no.
Yep, can see it.
Okay, good.
All right. So those were our two current event presentations.
I don't remember who's up next week, whoever signed up in the spreadsheet, but
we will have more next week on the
plasma environment. So one
thing
we might want to discuss is
why humans in space, and I love
this quote by Stephen Hawking
because we are looking at long-term survival of the
human race. It's kind of like
it was back in the days when we explored the West,
Western United States, and we started populating it.
It, right now, doesn't have a lot of rules and laws and
regulations, so who knows what it's going to come down
to. If we're the first on Mars, do we get to claim it? Who knows?
There's a lot of things associated with space law, and I
believe y'all have an option to take that class,
that are still needed to be answered, but more
importantly, can we even survive that
environment? So
what are some reasons, and let's just discuss them
verbally,
for humans in space?
Any thoughts there?
We'll just do a couple of these.
Because one thing is humans are
flexible and adaptable,
whereas if you have
a situation in space that has not been pre-planned
or pre-worked, an autonomous or robot
environment would not be able to
necessarily handle that situation.
So we are humans
and have a lot of benefits over
autonomous
solutions in exploring our solar
system.
This is one example, Luca
Parmitano. You may remember this
from his aborted spacewalk in 2013.
There was a leak in Luca's helmet,
and it turned out to be a carbon dioxide filter issue.
So let's listen to this.
This cleaner is insane. It removes baked-on
oven grease-
This is not it, by the way. This is a commercial
... from any surface without scrubbing, without bleach, and without
anything you'd be afraid to have around a toddler.
It was invented by a world-class-
I can skip it, though
Chris, guys, what do you think? It sounded like we just heard you cannot hear.
Is that true as well?
No, no, I can hear perfectly. I can still hear perfectly.
But my head is really wet,
and I am feeling very chilly.
And it is
possible, but I think maybe it will be better for me to come back.
Standby, Chris. Hi, Chris and Luca, just for you guys,
based on what we heard with Luca saying that water is in his eyes now, and it
seems to be increasing, we think we're going to terminate EVA case for
EV2. So Luca, we'll have you head back to the airlock.
Chris, we'll get a plan for you to clean things up here and then join him here in a
minute.
Move around
as I try to kick
them.
This is live footage, so that's why the sound is going in and out.
Alright, I'm looking for you guys.
Big picture, we're going to do a nominal repress if Luca can stand
that, except Luca's going to stay on battery, not SCU,
and...
Okay, we copy.
All...
Is that the lock?
Thermal cover
is closed. I'm in.
Copy. Thermal cover closed.
And I'm with you.
So, this is one reason why...
Whoops.
Hey, Luca, can you clarify-
Oh, there we go
... is it increasing or not increasing?
Let's stop that,
and
go back to my slides.
It's hard to tell, but it feels a-
Which I am having problems doing.
A lot of water.
There we go. There it
is.
It's all mixed with water.
So, one thing to notice in that
situation is
if that had been a robot, first off, they wouldn't
have had any issues. Well, my robot might have
issues with water,
but it wouldn't need it in the first place.
So,
that is one thing to keep in mind. Once you have humans on
board, then you have a lot of other
situations that you have to take care of.
The other thing to learn from that is that
situations like this,
ground control doesn't necessarily know what's going on.
They said at the beginning that he could not hear, and he's like, "No, I can hear
fine. I just can't breathe."
Or, "I'm getting to the point where I can't breathe." And it was
important to have a human there to tell
ground control what was going on, so that they could make the right
decisions. Now, the last time we lost human lives in
space was Columbia in 2003. Fortunately,
it's been a long time, when the ice hit the thermal protection
foam.
But
humans have been working in space
for 65 years. Yuri Gagarin
launched in 1961.
So we have figured out a lot about humans operating in the space environment.
So on to new challenges.
Next, I'd like to show just a
recap of some of the things that humans have done in
space. So let me get this started.
And this is a good
start for this discussion.
Okay, I'm having some problems
getting it on
my slides.
And show, there we go.
All right.
So here we go.
We
want to find out what's out there. We want to be able to expand our horizons.
I think that that truly is built into the human spirit.
We're always wondering, what's next? How much farther can we go?
The Mercury astronauts, when they get introduced, you immediately coalesce as sort
of the heroes. The press conference that NASA had goes crazy, and the
astronauts become instant celebrities.
They sort of look like knights in armor in some ways, going out there to defend the
honor of the United States.
Roger.
Lift off, and the clock has started.
I remember feeling a moment of exhilaration
because, of course, I had been training for two years, and in fact, I
was more than ready for the lift off to occur, and was quite
delighted that in fact, it did occur, and occurred so smoothly.
Roger.
We choose to go to the moon in this decade and do the other things,
not because they are easy, but because they are hard.
Game
It's outward bound. People have a
human feeling, I think, for wanting to go
outward bound. It's in us, to go, to see, to
touch, to understand what's there.
Ignition sequence start.
We finally come to the day, the moment.
The trajectory had been wrong. They were targeted into
this inhospitable place. Then they had to fly over
this area at a high forward velocity, then pitch
up to slow down, so they kill that forward velocity,
and then start down like a helicopter.
At Tranquility Base here, the Eagle has landed.
That's one small step for man,
one giant leap for
mankind.
The landing, to me, was a great celebration.
We had won the race. The nation was almost
euphoric.
The knowledge that we gained about the origin and the evolution of the Moon
is, one of these days, going to help us right here on Earth.
Of course, it's only one area, but I believe it's an important area, and I
guess I'm betting a lot on it.
NASA has been absolutely critical to improving the knowledge of all
humankind. Twelve humans walked on the surface of the Moon, which
is a stunning achievement, and we are still the only
country ever to have done that. We're going to go back to the Moon, and we're going
to take what we learned there, and we're going to go to Mars.
To get to Mars, it's about a six-month journey, and as an operator, I
would be really, really happy if we could test out our
operations and our equipment in our backyard. The Moon's only three days away.
The Moon is the next step.
The space station, more than a million pounds.
It's as big as two football fields.
You are not going to bring that up in one single lift.
So we had to bring up the space station in parts and assemble it.
The space shuttle was instrumental to bringing up at least the American side of
that. It was more than 40 missions over about 13 years to
assemble all those parts of the space station.
And so human spaceflight's really interesting because we do adapt
really quickly to the environment.
How quickly it felt natural to float around.
How quickly it felt normal to look out the window and see the Earth go
by.
Human beings are built to be able to adapt to
weightlessness, and that allows us to go do that exploration.
And so we have improved the exercise equipment.
We improved the diet and the vitamins.
We came back so strong that physically I was actually stronger than
when I left, when I did the physical fitness test when we got back.
Gives me great hope that if we have similar type of equipment on our long-duration
space vehicles, we're going to show up on Mars and be ready to work the minute we
get there.
Orion, our state-of-the-art spacecraft, is designed to take crews
into deep space, and then once their work is done, to safely bring them
back home. Sometimes folks ask me, "What do you think the
next 60 years has in store?" I don't
know all of the destinations that we will visit, the
mysteries that we will solve, the places that we will leave
footprints again.
And we want to see what's out there. We want to see how it works.
We want to go explore. There's always this desire to
learn more, to satisfy that inquisitive nature.
Let's go do it.
Subscribe for more of NASA's sixth-
I agree. Let's go do it.
Any thoughts on that video? Any takeaways?
It was a couple of years old. Bridenstine was still NASA
administrator, and of course, that's changed.
But I did want to point out
a couple of things about what... Whoops.
Go back to that slide. Okay. About why we
might want to...
We could ask that. Why we might want
to explore
space. So I don't know why it keeps doing that. Anyway.
Well,
200 years earlier, Lewis and Clark Expedition of the
American Northwest discovered a lot.
Shackleton and Amundsen and Scott explored
Antarctica 100 years ago. 500 years ago,
Columbus discovered the Americans.
Thousand years ago, Leif Erikson discovered
Greenland. We have the science and technology to
live and explore beyond low Earth orbit.
However, there have been less than
600 people who have flown in space, and only
12 who have landed on the Moon. So why
haven't we explored more? Well, there's a variety
of reasons, but mostly it comes down to money,
number one, and political changes,
because each administration seems to have different priorities.
Obama's was to go to asteroids.
Now, recently, there was a push there for a while to go to Mars.
Now, recently, it's been a push to go back to the Moon, except not just
back to the Moon, but to stay to provide a stepping
stone for some of those other destinations.
So why continue exploration? Well, there's five main
reasons. First off, it's human nature to
explore.
If you put your two-year-old in front of the stairs up
at the top of a stairway case,
and you tell them not good to go down, the first thing they're going to want to do
is go down the staircase. Well, it's human nature for us to want to
break out of our earthly
environment and explore more.
The second one I brought up when we looked at
Luca's helmet
accident or incident, and it's that
humans are flexible and adaptable, and I'll show some later
examples of that
tonight.
Also, and here is a very important reason, it inspires
future generations in STEM. All the excitement over
Artemis II, mostly because
there were humans involved,
got a lot of interest from the K through 12 community.
There's no doubt about that. So that helps our future.
It helps train future engineers,
technologists, astronauts,
everything that we need to continue to be strong as a
nation. It also keeps the United States in a
leadership role
in space.
And we're frankly, a little concerned that others will get there first.
And then finally, a good statistic is that
every dollar spent on the Apollo missions
resulted in a $7 to $8 return
through technology demonstrations that were
transferred to Earth solutions, new
jobs,
again, new products, things like that.
So those are five good reasons to keep us
exploring space.
Now, what are some challenges with that?
I picked this particular example
because I worked on it as a, was I a
lieutenant? Lieutenant or captain, I don't remember, in the Air Force,
and this is an example how we adapt and
overcome.
And one of the things in the Apollo program we were
looking at,
was
the max dynamic environment, max Q.
We thought that was the worst environment that you could have, either that
or liftoff.
Well, you can see from the chart here that liftoff is a
pretty extreme environment, but we expected that.
What we didn't expect is this whole
high acceleration involvement at about 20 to 30
seconds in this particular example.
And what we found out is that that
was due to a phenomenon called pogo.
And pogo occurs when the
first natural frequency of the launch vehicle
coincides with the propulsion subsystem.
The frequency
is proportional to, or actually, this is the
equation,
k over m,
where k is the stiffness, which
you can't do a whole lot about.
m is mass, and for a rocket,
as that rocket flew,
its mass decreases, increasing the natural
frequency of the propellant subsystem.
Now, at some point, and you can see clearly on the charts
here,
that coincided with the natural frequency of the
launch vehicle, and it created a pogo-like
environment. If you remember, well, you might be too young to remember, or maybe
they have them now, pogo sticks, it kind of bounced up and down.
Well, that's what was happening now.
We didn't know that at the time, and the early astronauts
were coming back with headaches and bloodshot eyes and things like
that. And it just so
happened that the frequency that
this pogo occurred at coincided
with the natural frequency of the eyeball.
And that's something we have to look out for,
is that certain natural frequencies
interfere or affect certain
organs. And these are just some examples
of frequencies we have to make sure we avoid in orbit
to prevent humans from getting
nauseous, sick,
affected in other ways by these frequencies.
These are some human body resonant frequencies.
Like I said before, the pogo
phenomena occurred at about
45, 50 hertz, and that was definitely in the range for the
eyeball
natural frequency. And the reason you don't want your natural
frequencies to coincide is that
represents a resonant frequency, and that is
a bad situation to get in because it worsens in its
amplitude,
and it makes people very uncomfortable
and could be debilitating
So I wanted to point that out in that these are some things
that we have overcome in the past. Now,
that being said, when I was a lieutenant or captain, I
don't remember, like I said,
Atlas V, this problem was solved back in the Apollo days.
What they did is they put what's called accumulators on the
launch vehicles. And the accumulators were basically
a fluid-type
mechanism that absorbed the
vibrations, absorbed the energy from the vibrations and lessened
them when pogo started to occur. That being said,
I come along in the '90s and here
we go, Atlas V is having the same issue.
And we quickly identified it as pogo and said it's
been solved. Put an accumulator in your vehicle.
They did that and all was happy. Now, fast-forward,
what was that, 30 years ago?
New Shepard has been having issues with pogo,
and it seems like we are going back and resolving the same
problem time after time with new
generations coming along. So that's why I like
to, in my lectures, cover some
information about
past
problems and solutions that we've got so that when
you are in the workforce, you can remember these
solutions and perhaps save our current generations a lot
of time and move on to problems that we haven't solved yet.
So that brings us to some problems we have solved.
We do know about
the atmosphere that's needed, and right now the International
Space Station flies at an atmosphere
similar to that that we have, and I think I covered this
last time,
on Earth. We have 21% oxygen
and about 79% nitrogen because
that's what we're used to.
And nitrogen is essentially an inert gas that passes through us,
and we're not really sure what the purpose is other than it helps
with plants and other things on Earth.
But having that same environment in
space that you have on Earth is very
important.
ISS is operated at sea
level temperature, which is 101.3
kilopascals or 14.7 pounds per square
inch.
There is a much more flexible survival range and emergency
range. Fortunately, we haven't had to get into
those pressure levels in
at least the flights that have survived.
And
oxygen or carbon dioxide is then
byproduct of breathing, is then
solved by having carbon dioxide
filters on board our manned vehicles.
Temperature.
These are nominal temperatures for
the ISS, and that's primarily where humans are right now.
Although China has their own space station,
and these are the max and min temperatures that we
would see on the Moon, Mars, and Ceres.
So keep in mind
that we need to duplicate as much as
possible our environment here on Earth that we
have in space.
And that is sometimes a very challenging thing to do.
We are very needy
because humans prefer the temperature to be
about plus or minus 10 degrees.
And
that gives us a much more narrow range
than being unprotected on the Moon, Mars,
Ceres, other planets or other moons or dwarf
planets.
And another thing to consider is that heat
energy generated by a
average size human in space
is about 100 watts per person, so you have to take
that into account with your thermal control system
because it will need to dissipate heat.
We generate heat just like a computer on your
desktop
or your laptop generates heat. In space,
and we talked about this maybe not a whole lot last time, but a little bit on
lesson one, there is no effective way to
dissipate heat other than radiation.
So human creation of
heat or human production of heat needs to be
accounted for.
Humidity.
The ISS target is about 40% to 60%
relative humidity. Their target is
46%.
Why? Because it helps with
comfort, equipment, safety, and efficient humidity
removal. So I grew up in the South. I know what high humidity
is about, and it can be very uncomfortable at times.
Now I live in Colorado and there's very little humidity,
and that can be a problem sometimes.
Oh, the picture on the left here. Germs can also
grow in high humidity environments.
So the picture on the left here was a
sample taken from the Mir Space Station of a water
droplet. And with that high humidity and just the human
biological systems going on,
these are actual microbes that had formed in that
water droplet, and that is not a good
situation for the astronauts to be in.
Think if those microbes landed in their mouth, that might be okay.
You could probably filter that out or kill them, but what if it landed in
an eye or an ear? And that would be
plausible because these water droplets are floating all around.
So the free-fall environment, we talked last time about how
something in orbit is actually falling
around that orbit, and that is
actually not zero gravity. You're still under the effect of
gravity or you'd go floating off into space.
That is called a microgravity. You're still
under about 91% of the Earth's
gravitational pull in LEO,
but more importantly, you're free-falling around the Earth,
and that gives you no contact forces.
So there are three main effects on humans.
The first is altered vestibular
functions.
And
I'll go into each of these a little later.
That means that your ability to sense what's up and down
interferes with your inner ear, and that keeps you off
balance. That was referred to in the first video that Shelby
put together. The second main effect, there's a lot of
effects, but these are the main effects.
We have reduced weight
on load-bearing tissues.
And that results in muscle loss, bone
loss,
and
those can lead to problems like, if I can spell
tissue,
those can lead to problems like
bone loss, which results in calcium loss,
which is why in the early days, the space station toilet used
to get clogged up a lot. They didn't plan on the large amounts
of calcium loss that the astronauts were getting
due to the bone density loss
and
had to design special
toilets for that reason. So if you hear the story about, "Oh, it's a
million-dollar toilet," well, it's not just a toilet that you would put in
your bathroom. There was a lot of design that went into
that, and I encourage you to look up details on how
the ISS toilets were designed because it's
absolutely fascinating. And then
finally, the last one
is reduced hydrostatic gradient.
And that means your water
on Earth tends to go towards your lower
extremities.
In space, there's no gravitational pull pulling it down.
You're in free fall, so that hydrostatic
gradient,
the water basically
floats throughout your body.
So what does this do? The reduced
hydrostatic gradient, you can see how
water
in a free fall environment creates a spherical shape,
whereas water droplets here on Earth create a
teardrop shape. Same thing happens with the fluids in your body.
So what that does is that tends to bring the
fluid towards the astronauts' heads, so they have a fat
face and
reduces the water in
the lower extremities. So we call that the fat face,
chicken legs phenomena.
You can see this in some astronaut pictures here.
On the left is
an astronaut on the ground. On the right is her in space.
You can see the fluid shift in her face as well as
this second one, which also demonstrates
the same thing.
Altered vestibular functions.
As I explained before, you no longer have a sense of
what's up and down. You can see that from these astronauts.
They're oriented in all different ways.
And this is your homework question two.
What is meant by altered vestibular functions
and what are its symptoms?
One thing that's interesting is that you can get an effect
called space adaptation syndrome, and I'll
talk about that in a few more slides.
Reduced load on weight-bearing tissues.
Long-term effects,
we don't really know. We've only been
in LEO and had humans in that situation
for usually way less than a
year, but one year or two years, something like that.
A long-duration Moon mission will put
astronauts at one-sixth the
Earth's gravitational pull on the Moon.
What will that do to an
astronaut on a long-term mission?
What's going to be the long-term effects of
taking six months to get to Mars? Now, Mars doesn't have
as strong as a gravitational pull that the Earth does,
but you can see here when astronauts come back to the Earth, this is
astronaut Nick Hague,
they
pretty much have to be carried
out of their landing capsule to give them a chance to
reorient themselves to the 1G environment.
Now, they do exercise a lot in space, usually two
hours a day, and that mitigates a lot of these
effects. But when we get to Mars
with our first crew, there's not going to be anyone there to carry
them out of their capsule. So how is six months
in a free fall environment or
zero-gravity environment going between
planets,
how is that going to affect them? And will they be
able to get up and recuperate in time to do
the things that they need to do on Mars, or Ceres, or wherever it is,
such as building a habitat, getting food set up,
getting robotics or rovers
set up to do their mission? So that's a big
question left out there. Who's going to carry them out
of their capsule when they get to Mars?
Ceres has a very low gravitational constant, so
that probably wouldn't be a problem, but Mars very well could.
What do we do to overcome that? We exercise
two hours a day on average,
and that includes weight,
which is basically done through resistive straps,
weight training, and cardio training.
There are, I think, currently two
treadmills on the ISS as well as a cycling
machine. Two hours a day is a significant amount of
time, and if you're already busy doing
an eight to 10-hour shift, and then you have to come off that and
do your two hours of exercise, then that
can sometimes be a problem.
Now, I referred to space
adaptation syndrome, and this is a quote from Stephen
Smith.
It's hard to predict who is going to be susceptible
to getting
the equivalent of car sick in that environment.
One thing that's interesting is that women have
been shown to be less susceptible to this effect than
men. And what we want to avoid at all
costs is to be in our astronaut suit and do that.
So,
we would like to better predict space
adaptation syndrome, but we do
know the trend is that men are more susceptible to
women.
So
the crew accommodations are built off of reduce,
reuse, recycle, and I'll go more
into the
logistics of how we do that in the next set of
slides. And we're also going to talk about psychological
effects
and a
anomaly
identification or
maybe even disaster identification of root causes
using a model called the Shell model, which is
often used in aircraft incidents.
So bottom line is reduce, reuse, and
recycle. Every ounce going into an astronaut's body
is accounted for, including sweat, urine, everything else
that you can think of, and that is then used to
carefully design the environment
to adapt to those situations.
So what we're going to go into now is called the Human
Research Roadmap, and this is a roadmap that NASA
has provided or developed
to mitigate some of those risks. So
basically, it is a risk
evaluation and reduction in about 99
different areas. It might be 100 by now, but 99 different areas,
and this is called the NASA Bioastronautics
Roadmap.
And I have
provided the link here
so you can get
familiar with it
because you will have a homework problem on this.
Couple
So first off,
like was mentioned in one of the previous videos,
humans have an amazing
ability to adapt to our environment, and that includes the
space environment. So we, as well with
other mammals,
all
life forms actually, adjust to environmental
conditions. So an example here is the camel.
It has adapted to live in a
very dry
environment
and
what happens is they are able to
consume large amounts of water and store them in
their bodies. So that's an example, not to compare humans to camels,
but that is an example of adaptation.
So like I said before,
physiological adaptation is a huge concern.
The bodily adjustments we make as we strive to
maintain equilibrium is
sweat if it's too hot, goosebumps if
it's too cold.
And as
we are adapting to the free fall environment,
we, like I said before, have less muscle mass because it's just not
needed in free fall, and more calcium
losses due to the reduction
in weight bearing on the bones.
Behavioral is the
choices we make to prevent or cope with the harsh
conditions or their consequences.
Some things that astronauts regularly do is they make sure
they're on a good routine of vitamins and calcium,
especially to replace some of that calcium loss in their
bones, exercise, and a balanced
diet, which is typically selected
several months before flight.
The crew shown here,
they were only in space for
128 days, and we have a
Russian, Japanese, I don't remember their names, but on the right I do know is
Sunita Williams, and they were getting carried off of their
mission.
What were some of our first experiences in space?
Well, we talked about Laika last time on Soyuz 2,
but some of the first
US experiments involved rhesus
monkeys,
and I won't show the video here. There is an embedded
video that you can take a look at. It might be on the next page.
And
some of the first monkeys we've flown, you may have heard the couple,
Abel and Miss Baker. They flew in
1959.
And what a lot of people don't know is that they came back
alive, but Abel died four
days after the return due to some infections,
due to some of the equipment that they stuck into him
on the flight. So Abel actually died.
Miss Baker, went on to live
to the ripe age of 27. For a rhesus monkey, that's pretty good.
In Huntsville, Alabama.
They both went to
kilometers, and they were the first to survive the
landing and live.
Before,
in 1947, we started small. We started with fruit
flies and were able to show that they
survived to 109 kilometers. But you might be
wondering
what happened between the fruit flies in
1947 and Abel and Miss Baker
in 1959. Well, we did a lot of experiments.
In 1948, Albert I
was sent up on a rocket,
and he died of suffocation.
In 1949, Albert II died of
parachute failure. Albert III was on
a V2 rocket that exploded at 35,000 feet.
Albert IV died of parachute failure, and by this point, I
would say let's not name any more Albert, but they went on doing it
anyway. Albert V died of parachute
failure.
Albert VI in 1951, and
11 mice flew, and the mice
survived, but Albert later died due
to excessive heat.
1959, we talked about Abel and Miss Baker.
Miss Baker survived for a long time.
1961, Ham the chimp
survived and lived in DC for 17 years, a ripe old age for a monkey
or for a chimp. And the Soviets used
dogs mostly for their experiment.
So in the Russians' eyes,
they said, "Let's get the rest of the chain.
Dogs are enough like humans, so let's send a human into space." Yuri Gagarin
in April 12, 1961, and
the Vostok capsule spent one hour and
48 minutes in a 169 times
327-kilometer orbit.
Alan Shepard, thank goodness he wasn't named Abel,
or Albert,
flew on May 5th, 1961. So we let the Russians do it first,
prove it could be done, and then we flew ours on a Mercury
Redstone. It was a 15-minute
suborbital flight that went to 187 kilometers.
The first reported cosmonaut death was during ground
training. Valentin Bondarenko in
'61 was burned in a fire in an oxygen-rich,
low-pressure isolation chamber.
That, however, was not
reported to the world until 1986. And as
you may have heard, our Apollo 1 mission
ended up with the death of three astronauts due to the same
thing on the ground. They were going through testing,
and they were in an oxygen-risk environment.
A spark underneath the seat caused a fire.
The pressure difference kept them from getting out, and all three
died. So there have been a lot of losses in
our space program.
Bottom line is that animal flights indicated that humans might have
some difficulty adapting to space and surviving in space.
The Apollo missions were, of course,
1969, Armstrong, Collins, and Aldrin
were the first to land on the moon. They ate hot dogs, drank
coffee, and gathered about 20 pounds of moon rocks,
and they left an American flag, scientific equipment,
and some jettisoned items.
So what enables us to survive? Well, that would
be our life support systems. And
you need to recognize or need to
understand that the volume percent
oxygen
varies with pressure.
As pressure
goes down, we need more oxygen.
But it's a very thin line here. So you have to stay in this
region
here,
depending on the pressure, to keep humans
healthy and without getting the phenomena of
hypoxia. I showed you that
lesson one, the astronaut's hand,
the glove came off
during vacuum testing, and it suffered from
hypoxia, that is low oxygen.
And then the other thing can happen on the other end, you can get too much
oxygen and get oxygen
toxicity or hyperoxia,
and that can cause swelling and
other problems that are very bad.
Too much
hyperoxia can cause
disorientation,
seizures, and other bad effects like that,
whereas too little or the oxygen depletion can
cause altitude sickness. And you see a lot of people go up to Pikes Peak
and get that
because of the fact that air
is
less dense up there and has less oxygen.
Thing you need to remember about spacewalks is you have to
carry everything along with you. In the International Space
Station, most of that is pretty developed and has been used
for many, many years. Spacewalk, however, you need
to provide oxygen, water,
ability to speak,
ability to hear, carbon dioxide removal,
everything that a human needs to survive.
So this is the example I was talking about.
Apollo 1 on January 27,
1967, Ed White, Gus Grissom, and Roger
Chaffee
were training in their Apollo
command module, which was supposed to fly.
And an arcing under the seat in the pure
oxygen environment caused a
fire. And the escape
hatch wouldn't open because the fire increased the cabin
pressure.
That brought out about a major redesign on Apollo
to be about 34% oxygen, and now we have
stabilized it out to be about what it
is here on Earth.
So the atmosphere is a huge driver of requirements,
especially for structure and power requirements.
What do we do on the ISS when an astronaut is getting ready
to go out for a
spacewalk?
An EVA
for the US
is done at about
29.6 kilopascals.
Russia
is about
39.2
kilopascals. So we haven't necessarily
agreed on that and handle it a little
differently. Pre-breathing is always a
requirement because it washes out nitrogen, that inert
gas that we're breathing in all the time.
So they do 100% oxygen
Without any possibility of sparks or anything like that
at
one hour
sea level pressure, 101.3 kilopascals
or 14.7 pounds per square inch.
Russia, on the other hand, that would be US.
Russia, on the other hand, only does 30 minutes.
So they have decided that their astronauts are a little more
robust than ours, apparently.
Decompression sickness, the reason we wash out the nitrogen
is that you can get bends like you do
with deep-sea diving if
you do not account for it.
The supersaturated nitrogen forms gas bubbles, and it can go into
the brain, give you stroke-like symptoms, but more
important or more likely is just a case of the bends,
where the nitrogen gets involved in the tissues and creates tremendous
pain.
The R factor
is
given by the partial
pressure of nitrogen
in the habitat
over the partial pressure of nitrogen
in the suit,
and that is called
R,
which is called the bends ratio.
Pretty fitting term.
The lower the R, the easier it is to
adapt. The lower the difference between the two, or even if the
habitat is lower than the suit,
it's easier to adapt. So an R of about
1.5 is ideal.
For US EVAs,
the pressure is kept at 29.6
versus 39.2.
The US will operate
at eight hours on spacewalks,
or EVAs, and the Russians will
operate at a maximum of seven.
Their equipment
for the US
is about 55 kilograms, not that it matters because they're in
free fall, which is about 122 pounds, whereas
for the Russians, they have about 120 kilograms or
260 pounds of life support.
Okay, so here is an
example of what can go wrong. It is
called decompression blues, the Soyuz
disaster. So let's take a look at this.
Here we go.
Not advertising pizza.
Salyut 1, the first space station, was launched unmanned from the Soviet Union on
April 19th, 1971. Two days later,
Soyuz 10 lifted off carrying a crew of three toward the station.
The mission was to remain in space for 30 days.
The cosmonauts attempted to dock with Salyut 1, but although they were able to lock
onto the station, a problem with the hatch kept them from being able to enter it.
Once the soft connection is secured, if both spacecraft are pressurized, they
may proceed to a hard dock, where the docking mechanisms form an airtight
seal, enabling interior hatches to be safely opened.
Then, the crew and cargo can be transferred.
But the automatic control system failed during approach due to a serious
design flaw.
Soft dock was achieved on 24 April 1971 at
1:47 AM, but the computer sensed an abnormality in the spacecraft's
alignment and began firing the attitude control jets to lose balance.
With Soyuz 10 being pushed to one side by the attitude control system, it
became impossible to achieve hard dock.
The docking attempt was called off.
They returned home early and unsuccessful.
On June 6 of the same year, Soyuz 11 transported
cosmonauts Georgi Dobrovolski, Vladislav Volkov, and Viktor
Patsayev to Salyut 1, where after three hours, the spacecraft
successfully docked with the station, and the cosmonauts remained on board for
23 days, setting a new record. They became the first men to live
aboard on an Earth-orbiting spacecraft.
Their mission wasn't without its problems.
On June 16th, smoke from a control panel caused the crew to consider
abandoning the station, but the unit was switched off, and the problem averted.
On June 30th, they left Salyut 1 and began re-entry procedures.
When the crew fired the explosive bolts to separate the Soyuz 11 re-entry
capsule from the spacecraft, a critical valve was jerked open.
100 miles above the Earth, the capsule was suddenly exposed to the environment of
space, depressurizing the interior of the ship.
Cosmonauts at the time did not wear suits while in flight.
As the capsule rapidly depressurized, Patsayev tried to close the valve
by his hand. Minutes later, the cosmonauts were dead.
But how does death by depressurization feels like?
In 1965, a technician at Johnson Space Center in Houston
lived to tell about the experience.
While inside a vacuum chamber, the tech accidentally depressurized the suit he
was wearing. His last memory before losing consciousness was the
sensation of the moisture on his tongue beginning to boil.
The expert stated some of the possible symptoms of rapid decompression as
swollen flesh, vaporizing blood, exploding eyeballs, and ruptured
lungs.
While Salyut 1 remained in its orbit, no further trips were made to the
station. On October 11th, 1971, the engines on
Salyut 1 fired for the last time, bringing the space station into a lower
orbit that would result in its eventual plunge into the Pacific Ocean.
Okay, we can get rid of the haunted pizza ad, but
that
is just some of the things
that you have to be careful about and plan for
in
a mission like that. So what happened?
We called it decompression blues.
Let me go on to the next slide.
They boarded the space station, Salyut 1, from 7 to
30 June 1971, and it appeared to be a normal
re-entry, but it killed all three of them.
The breathing ventilation valve jolted open during
descent. Model separation from the service module,
and the explosive valves, here's the bottom line of what happened.
The explosive bolts fired
simultaneously instead of sequentially like they
were supposed to. So just a small mistake like
that can result in the death of humans because
we're very needy and need a lot of things.
So all of them died
of those effects you saw in the video.
Other requirements, we have carbon dioxide.
It's about .03% on Earth.
Even 10 times that, there's little effect
on humans,
but I do want to point out, I don't know if you've ever read the book,
"Endurance" by Scott Kelly. He talks about
the real-life experiences and
the things that happened in a lot of intricate detail, so don't
let your kid read it.
But in "Endurance" by Scott Kelly, he talks
about how he could tell when
the carbon dioxide in the environment in the
ISS got too high or too low because
he would get headaches, rapid fatigue,
and he could definitely feel the symptoms.
So that's why the ISS uses a carbon
dioxide removal assembly and
zeolite to help filter out that
CO2.
Humidity, like I said before, is kept between about 25% and
70%,
and
ventilation airflow. Lack of airflow can be a big
problem because you can get still air, and airborne
particles can build up, and the CO2 can build up, and it's
got nowhere to go. So if CO2 comes along and hovers
over your mouth, that would be a bad situation.
For ventilation, the ISS uses about 0.08 to
0.2 meters per second
in localized fans because there is air in that environment,
and about 0.4 meters per second in
exercise areas. Contaminants have to be taken
special care of at home. The typical
contamination level, assuming you keep your house clean,
is about 10 micrograms per meter cubed.
On the ISS, it is about 200
micrograms per meter cube because there is just
nowhere for it to go.
The other thing you need to consider is acceleration limits,
and if you've ever wondered why astronauts are
positioned on their backs during liftoff, it
is because you can handle much higher
entry impact and G rates,
and the x-axis is through your back, the y-axis is through your side,
and the z-axis is through your head,
oriented in the back
while they're laying on their back.
Sleeping is sometimes a unusual experience.
Some of them choose to use straps, some of them don't.
The arms and the body tend to go into
a comfortable position sometimes, kind of like a fetal position,
unless they strap themselves down.
How do you bathe in space? Well, they use dry shampoo,
but for long
hair, the hair goes
somewhat
haywire, and tying it in pigtails doesn't
help a whole heck of a lot. Metabolic balance.
Every ounce in and out of an astronaut's
body is accounted for, except for that
nitrogen, it's inert.
And a typical astronaut gets about five kilograms per
day in and out, which is about 11 pounds,
and that includes water, gases, solids,
et cetera.
Potable water,
3.5 kilograms per day. In an emergency,
that can go down to three kilograms per day or
five during heavy work. Total, including hygiene,
is typically about 30 kilograms per day.
So the water requirements on this chart include
the effects of hygiene.
Water recycling is done
basically on everything that
can be done.
Human factors. What keeps humans comfortable?
Space requirements. Well,
you might wonder
or you might
realize that
there are different per capita space
requirements or space available per person on Earth,
but in space, we're not interested so much in
area, we're interested in volume.
So the habitable volume is
the usable space. Absolute
minimum would be tolerable about five cubic meters per
person. Optimal would be 17
cubic meters per person, and that is a large quantity.
So,
for long-duration space missions, the Orion
capsule does not provide that
optimal performance capability,
so we need some longer-term solutions.
So that brings us to what NASA has been doing in some of these
areas, the Bioastronautics
Roadmap.
They compared risk for
three missions. The
first is less than 30 days in the ISS.
Actually, four. The second is one year on the
ISS, the third is one-month mission to the
moon, and the
fourth is a 30-month round-trip
Mars, which is
about two and a half years on
average. And they have considered 45 risk
areas. The human is considered to be the critical
system of spaceflight. So the goal is to
reduce risk through effective and efficient
mitigation solutions. So in this research
roadmap, and I won't go into all the details here, we will
identify and assess the risk, and prioritize the
research. So for each mission,
they evaluated, it might be more than 45, I haven't
looked lately, but
45 risk areas that include some of these
hazards. There are three levels.
There is no mitigation strategy,
which means that would be things like
radiation.
The red regions would be that.
Radiation, medical things, even toothaches would go
in that category.
Number two would be the yellow regions,
and
these require some mitigation
techniques, better filters, better toilets, that sort of
thing. And then if anything's green, we have good
mitigation in place. We have exercise for the
ISS. We have
sleep
medications that can help with sleep, that sort of thing.
So the definition of these four missions are, like I said, low-Earth
orbit, lunar orbit, or lunar orbit and surface, and Mars.
Five main hazards: altered gravity,
microgravity, radiation, isolation and confinement in hostile
closed environment, and distance from the Earth.
So this chart just explains those
likelihood times consequence
ratings. So if you have a low likelihood and a
low consequence, then that would be a
green. A low
likelihood, but a
higher
consequence, then that would be a yellow, so forth and so on.
So this explains that. I'll let you look into the details because I've
provided the reference for
this. Risk step. Disposition, I already covered
this. Requires characterization, requires mitigation,
transferred, or retired, which means it's
no longer a risk.
These are just a few of the risk areas,
and this is what you will find under each
risk area. LEO, lunar orbital, or lunar
orbital for bone changes, for example.
For cardiovascular, a lot of that has been
mitigated.
Dust exposure, if we go to a surface like Mars, we
have some very risky
situations we can get into there. And then altered immune
systems, that's in pretty good shape.
Reduced muscle size, we can reduce that by
exercise programs.
Sensory and vestibular functions, lunar
orbital and surface, both short and long duration
requires mitigation methods that we haven't come up with yet.
And then food and nutrition, if we're going
on a Mars mission, that would be an extremely high
risk.
So, where next? Like I was talking about before, I will not
show this video. It is linked in here.
We looked several years ago at a
human mission to Ceres, and what I
have assigned you for homework problem
five is to look at the
NASA BioAstrix roadmap and
extend it to Ceres operational, which would
be short-term, maybe two or three months, you'll have to come up with that
definition, and Ceres long-term, and see
what type of risk areas you think would be applicable
for each of those. So complete the columns for
this BioAstrix roadmap for a Ceres
mission. Choose three specific areas and discuss them more
thoroughly, and how the risk would be different
for Ceres, and what might be a good mitigation
strategy for that risk.
So,
this is in a quick summary.
What we've talked about, we've talked about different things today
about the
bioastronautics environment in
both short-duration and long-duration flight.
And you have a couple of homework assignments to look into.
Now, lecture is not over. I do have one more part that I need to share
with you,
and give me just a moment to
pull that up.
And that is the Shell Model and
psychological aspects.
So, this is actually a very fascinating topic.
I could spend hours and hours on this,
but we don't have that much time. You'll have to do some of this research
yourself.
And we will start with
the psychological aspect, group dynamics, and the Shell Model.
The Shell Model is important because I'm going to ask you
to analyze a couple of different scenarios using
this.
So, when most people think about the challenges of
space flight, they think about rockets blowing
up, orbital mechanics, the life support systems going down.
But very seldom,
one of the most important and often overlooked components of any space
mission is the people's psychological
status.
So we're going to explore the human side of spacecraft over the
next 40 minutes or so, how astronauts respond
to stress, and how crews function as teams in
isolated and confined environments, because the
psychological aspect is actually very important.
We will also examine the Shell Model.
It started in use for
airplane
disasters and aviation,
but it helps us understand how humans interact with
hardware, software, procedures, other people in their
environment. And you'll find that many of the space disasters,
some of which we've already talked about,
weren't caused by a single technical failure.
It resulted from very complex interactions between people and
complex systems.
And what we're going to consider in this block is that astronauts
are one of the spacecraft's most critical subsystems,
and understanding human performance as just as
important as understanding propulsion techniques,
structures, astrodynamics, et cetera.
So, we'll start by looking at what we've learned
about human performance in space over the last 60 years.
One of the biggest surprises, and we talked
about this in the first part of this lecture, is that one of
the biggest surprises is that humans are actually much more adaptable
than we originally believed,
and we put that at the center in this discussion
of the design. When humans are on board, humans
are our number one priority.
The Apollo 11 mission. I do have a video to go with this, but I
will not show it
I'll let you show that yourself,
is Apollo 11, the first lunar landing.
Obviously, you know that. But it was not just a technical
challenge, but an enormous psychological challenge as well.
And Neil Armstrong, Buzz Aldrin, and Michael Collins were operating
in an environment no human had ever experienced,
because there was no possibility of quick rescue,
the communications with the Earth were delayed, and that has improved
over the years, and every single decision carried
tremendous consequences.
Some of the things you might not know,
so if you want to look into the details, watch the embedded
video. As they approached the lunar surface, the guidance
computer began issuing unexpected program alarms.
Of course, when you rely on computers, they start doing strange things.
Mission Control quickly determined that they could be ignored, but the
crew
didn't know that. It took that communication delay, and they had to
process that information while continuing to land
very shortly on the Moon.
Then, Neil Armstrong realized that the computer was guiding the
Eagle towards a field of large boulders.
So he had to take manual control, a very split-second decision,
all while fuel reserves continued to
dwindle. By the time he found a good landing
situation and the Eagle had landed, they only
had about 20 to 30 seconds of
usable fuel left. So what made
this mission successful were four main
factors: the crew's ability to remain calm,
to communicate effectively, to prioritize the
information, and to make sound
decisions under extreme stress. And that doesn't come
by accident. The astronaut training program, which sometimes I'd
cover
if we had more time, has very
extensive psychological checks
and investigations in place to make sure that
astronauts can handle situations like this.
The other thing that was on their side is that they had years of
training,
and that had prepared them for situations that no flight
simulator predicted this stuff would happen
could fully reproduce.
Apollo 11 reminds us that astronauts are not simply
operators of a spacecraft. They are adaptive
problem-solvers, and in many situations, they
become the last line of defense when unexpected
events occurred. So what characteristics
allowed them to succeed?
Number one, extensive training. Number two, situational
awareness. Number three, calm under pressure.
Number four, effective crew communication,
and there is a five, good decision-making
despite incomplete information.
And we will see that psychology and
group dynamics often determines whether the
technology succeeds or fails.
So there is a video you can watch,
but before we can understand how astronauts cope with stress,
let's define it. We often say someone is stressed, but
technically, stress is not the event itself.
The event is the stressor. The stress is the
body's response to that stressor.
So I provided the Merriam-Webster and American Institute
of Stress
definitions here, and the
important thing to note out of the American Institute of Stress'
definition is that it is when a person
perceives that demands exceed the
personal and social resources.
Two people can experience the exact same situation and
have completely different stress responses.
One could
interpret it or perceive it as a challenge.
Another might perceive it as overwhelming.
Stressful situations for astronauts include launching aboard a rocket that could
blow up at any minute, conducting a
spacewalk, or responding to an onboard
emergency, and that would be stressful for most
everyone.
But astronauts are carefully screened based on training,
experience, their confidence level in being able to handle
stressors, personality, and the
support of help available to them.
Physical stressors are things that we've talked about
already, noise,
vibration, microgravity, disturbed sleep, radiation
exposure, but here are just a few
of the psychological
stressors.
Isolation.
Got people around you, but you might be isolated
from your support system. Confinement.
You can't just go out for a walk.
Heavy workloads.
Time pressure. These are just a few
of
The most extreme stressors,
knowledge that help is not within reach.
Lack of control is a big one.
You can't really control what is happening
environmentally or with Mission Control.
So those are just a few stressors astronauts might
be under.
People's response to stressors. I saw this for the first time when I
was working on my PhD, getting ready to take my qualifying exams.
It was explained to me that there is an optimal
level of stress. Stress is not always negative.
A moderate amount of stress can do things like
sharpen attention, improve performance,
and keep astronauts alert during critical operations.
Problems arise when that stress becomes
prolonged or it exceeds an individual's
ability to cope. Chronic stress can
impair judgment, reduce
or impact teamwork, and affect your physical
health. And I think we've all experienced that,
upset stomach, sweaty palms, that sort of thing.
So it's not good to have no stress, then you're in a position of not really
caring what happens on. There's not a good position to be in too much
stress, but a little bit of stress is optimal because that
makes you care about what that outcome is.
So how do people respond to it?
That is called coping, of course.
And coping is a person's response to stressors through their
physiology, emotions, and behaviors.
So it's not simply how someone feels,
it's how they react mentally, physically, and socially.
So you might think about what happens before
a
very high-weighted exam.
And if you have exam anxiety like I do, you might relate to
these. Some physical effects might be your heart rate
increases, your palms become sweaty.
You actually have trouble concentrating.
Emotionally, you might feel anxious or frustrated,
and behaviorally, some people might use
that stress to become more focused and organized, but others
may procrastinate or withdraw,
and those are all valid coping responses.
Astronauts experience the same thing, but in a much more
demanding environment. Imagine
troubleshooting
a spacecraft that malfunctioned under
these conditions. You're floating in microgravity.
You have limited sleep.
The ISS is notorious for having
very constant background noise, and
an astronaut was recently rescued in about a few days,
but
the ability to get that help immediately is not there.
So the ability to manage stress effectively becomes just as
important as technical competence.
That's why it's such a big part of the astronaut selection
program.
Types of coping or program focus
coping.
Program-focused
and emotion-focused.
Problem-focused is focused on reducing the source
of the stress, and some things astronauts can do
to eliminate that or reduce that stress is to
use checklists, follow procedures closely,
ask Mission Control for assistance, and
carefully divide tasks among the crew.
Emotion-faced coping is managing your
emotional response. So
rather than eliminating the problem, sometimes you can't eliminate the problem,
so what can help there is maintaining
routines, exercising, staying connected with
family, practicing relaxation techniques,
using humor, or talking about your concerns with
someone. The best astronauts are
skilled at both. Most of us
are only good at one or the other. Best astronauts are skilled at
both. So think about the last time you were under significant
stress. In which of these manners
did you respond in? Or maybe the answer is both.
One thing that helps is to have a strong link to mission goals.
People cope with stress better when they
understand why they are enduring it, and a great
example of that is Apollo 13.
The explosion happened,
and they had one clear goal that became their number one goal,
get everyone home alive. That single
objective unified every decision made by both the
crew and Mission Control, and a clear mission
reduced confusion, minimized conflict, and helped everyone
prioritize.
On the ISS, it's often stressful because they
work 10 to 12-hour days for months on end.
But They do it because of the mission.
Most of the experiments that they're doing won't benefit them
personally, but they know they're contributing to
scientific knowledge and preparing humanity for future
exploration.
Prevention. One of the biggest misconception about
aerospace psychology is that psychologists are mainly
there to treat astronauts when something goes wrong.
In reality, it's almost the opposite.
80% of a psychologist's work takes place before the
mission even begins, and the goal is prevention
rather than treatment.
This comes in several ways. It
comes in the selection process. Even brilliant individuals
struggle if they can't collaborate under pressure.
The second is training. Astronauts spend years preparing for
situations that they hope will never happen.
Number three is they train together, and they have trust and shared
expectations. And number four is NASA is
continually working to optimize that environment.
So from NASA's perspective, it's much easier to prevent
psychological problems than to solve them
350 kilometers from Earth, or if we're going
further, it could be
hundreds of kilometers or even millions.
The photo on the left shows one of the astronauts cutting
another astronaut's hair,
and I don't remember what the names of these astronauts are,
but I do remember reading about this.
And incidentally, the
male astronaut said that
cutting her hair was the most stressful situation
he ever had
in his life. So stressful situations can come
up in many different situations. So instead of
asking, "What's wrong with this astronaut?"
We are asking, "How does the entire system influence this
astronaut's performance?" There are three
main components. The crew.
Successful crews are built around trust, communication,
mutual respect, and complementary
skills. The flight environment, even
small environmental factors, poor lighting, uncomfortable
temperatures, CO2 levels, excessive noise,
can gradually increase stress and reduce
performance.
And then number three, the organizational conditions.
Everything happening back on Earth, the mission planning, the leadership,
communication with mission control, scheduling, workload,
operational procedures, and overall culture of the
organization. So the bottom line here is that psychological
performance isn't determined by a single factor.
It's the result of an entire system working together or
sometimes working against itself.
A good example of that is the Mars 500 isolation
experiment. This was done by Russia,
and the European Space Agency, and the goal was to find out
if six people can remain psychologically healthy
and work together during the equivalent of a mission to Mars.
So it lasted 520 days between
June 2010 and November 2011.
And the psychological health depended on
several factors is what they found.
They found it depended on their workload, their
communication with mission control, and they did simulate
the 20-minute delay in communication that you would have with
the real Mars mission.
They had cultural differences. They had
changes in their sleep
schedule, and they also had the physical environment to
deal with.
What they learned from this experiment, and I encourage you to do a little bit of
research on your own, is that different people responded
differently. Can you imagine being in, it's a relatively big
habitat, but you can see in the picture in the middle
here, but can you imagine being there for
520 days with the same five
other people?
They also determined that sleep became a major issue
because they simulated a real
Mars mission. So there was irregular
circadian rhythms that led to reduced alertness.
They could
measure that. Lower motivation, slower reaction times,
and decreased productivity. And the motivation changed over
time, especially in the third quarter. That's called the third quarter phenomena.
So,
at the beginning, they were very motivated.
Second, they were still kind of motivated. The third came along.
We don't really have the motivation to continue it, but we
will. And then the fourth quarter, they pep back up.
And then communication delays changed the
way leadership worked because with a long communication delay like
that, you have to rely on your crew members to make a lot
of decisions.
And then number five is that small environmental
factors matter.
Mars 500 taught us that sending humans to Mars is not
primarily an engineering problem, it's a human
systems problem
And that is why NASA considers
astronauts as one component of a much larger integrated system
where the crew, spacecraft, and organization must all work
together.
So how do we keep crews connected?
Linkages and knowledges, good communications, and
delays can make conversations,
communicating back and forth, a matter of
hours, not just a few minutes like it is from the ISS.
Knowledge, onboard expertise, detailed procedures, intelligent
software, extensive cross-training.
Within the crew, they're kind of your surrogate family.
And the mission, how does their daily work
contribute to the larger goals?
Interpersonal stressors. I like Eugene Cernan's quote here,
"Imagine spending days looking back
at Earth." So this was something that he described as a profound
psychological change. National borders disappear.
Wars, politics, many everyday frustrations
seemed insignificant compared to the fragility of the entire
planet.
And on return,
he reported a stronger appreciation for family, a greater concern
for protecting the Earth, and a renewed sense of humanity's shared
future.
But there are some downsides.
Some astronauts, upon returning, have a difficult time
reconnecting with everyday life because people cannot
truly understand what they experience, so they can also
experience isolation due to that.
And as a result of that, NASA recognized that the
psychological support doesn't end when the spacecraft
lands. Astronauts need help, kind of like coming back from war,
reintegrating with the family and adapting back to normal
routines and processing the emotional
impacts, which are all important parts of
maintaining long-term behavioral health.
So one way we can analyze incidents or accidents or
anomalies is through the Shell Model,
and that is shown here.
We've seen that astronauts don't operate in isolations.
Their thoughts, emotions, relationships, and environment all
influence how they perform.
So how do engineers, investigators, and management
systematically analyze these interactions?
The Shell Model was originally developed in aviation and
has since become one of the most widely
used human factor models in aviation,
spaceflight, and other high-risk industries.
So let's start with the center of the
model, that is liveware, in other words, the
human being or the astronaut.
Software, on the left, refers to procedures,
checklists, training, regulations, mission
rules, and documentation. It's not just computer
software, it's all the information that tells people how to perform their
jobs.
Hardware is the physical equipment: spacecraft
controls, displays, spacesuits, tools,
life support systems, everything that astronauts
touch and operate. And the environment includes
both the physical surroundings such as
microgravity, radiation, noise, temperature, lighting, confinement,
and the operational environment that we're talking about in this class,
as well as workload and time pressure.
And the bottom L
represents interactions with other people: fellow
astronauts,
mission control, engineers, medical teams, family members on Earth.
What happens if you're on Mars and a family member dies, for
example? What's the procedures for that?
And accidents and dangerous
situations rarely result
from just one failure.
Apollo 7. Let's see. I don't have an embedded video
here, but
I should.
Maybe not. Anyway,
Apollo 7. Don't just ask yourself what
happened, ask yourself
what interfaces in the Shell Model.
So I'll do this example, and then we
will wrap it up.
So I have to go to my Links page.
This is an interesting case study because it actually
involved a little mutiny here, so-
When I started drinking warm water to help with my memory, my friends laughed at
me. But when they saw how much I'd improved, they started doing it
themselves. You've probably heard that as you get older, your memory will never
be the same.
We can skip that.
Day two.
The Apollo 7 team knows that the command module works.
But things with the crew are not
going well.
And then shut it down.
Wally Schirra came down with a monster head cold.
Schirra's cold is misery in orbit.
In the zero-gravity capsule, his sinuses just won't drain,
and he quickly becomes irritable
On Earth, astronauts might turn to comfort food when they're sick.
In space, there's really no such thing.
The space foods on the table here represent different meals throughout the day.
So we have sugar-coated cereal,
sausage patties, so this would make a nice breakfast.
We have chicken stew, which would've been a lunch or a dinner item, and then
butterscotch pudding and grapefruit drink.
First experiments in space food were cautious.
Could astronauts even swallow in space?
Nobody really knew.
In 1962, John Glenn proved that astronauts can
eat,
at least from a tube.
He could choose applesauce or pureed beef.
Early space food isn't very appetizing.
Scientists freeze-dry and dehydrate it into bite-sized morsels
and coat it with gelatin to stop down crumbs.
In space, crumbs don't fall, they float,
and air filters could pick up those crumbs, and it would just create a maintenance
problem for the astronauts, where they would need to clean those filters more
often.
By the time of Apollo 7, added features make space food a
bit more delicious.
Wally Schirra, Donn Eisele, and Walt Cunningham could
rehydrate things that had a bit more flavor and dimension to them, dishes that
might be more enjoyable and have some added flavors as well.
Quite a lot of concern down here.
But none of it is mom's chicken soup.
No they're not.
The mood in the command module quickly goes south.
It made Schirra, in particular, a little bit grumpy.
Flight director Glenn Lunney isn't used to hearing no,
even from one of NASA's stars.
I think it came as a bit of a shock to some of the people
on the ground that you have a space crew that's not necessarily going to do
everything you want them to do.
Is it possible to work that out?
Schirra thinks the workload is way too much.
When Wally had a cold, everybody had to be miserable.
On the final descent, mission control tells the crew to put on their
helmets.
Try them on this morning.
The crew refuses.
Now, if we had an open visor, I'd go along with that.
Schirra didn't want to do this because they needed to be able to clear their
ears as the pressure changed during the
descent.
Okay, I guess you better be prepared to discuss in some detail when we land why we
haven't got them on. But it's your neck, and I hope you don't break it.
Even before the astronauts are back on Earth, mission controllers
swear that none of them will ever fly
again.
Okay, so I don't know if you've ever heard that story before, but I
think it's kind of interesting because it shows
a lot of... Let's see. Where is it at? Here we go.
A lot of the challenges that can come between
mission control and the astronauts
if things like this aren't accounted for.
So let's take this in the concept of the Shell Model.
So ask yourself, was it the people?
Was it the procedures, the environment, the
hardware, or a combination of several factors?
Whoops. Let me try this share again.
Okay. So,
what happened? Well, the Apollo 7 mission
was only 11 days, and their goal was to test
the service module that would be going to the moon,
and it also had a command module on
there. Wally Schirra, he
was the commander. He had flown a lot of missions before that.
He did the third orbital flight in Mercury in
1962.
He flew a Gemini 6 near rendezvous with Gemini
7.
He was on the first manned Apollo flight and had a
significant amount of space experience, 300 hours.
However, based on this incident,
this was the last flight for all of these astronauts.
Walt Cunningham was supposed to be the lunar module pilot,
even though it wasn't flown on this mission.
Donn Eisele was supposed to be the command module pilot.
But as you heard in the video,
they came down with colds, and that is
why future astronauts are quarantined before they go into
space to make sure we don't have a repeat of something like
this.
Other things that the video didn't explicitly
mention is that the astronauts threw out some valuable
experiments because they thought they were overworked
and
just threw them out.
And Schirra had a strained relationship with ground
control because, like it said in the video,
if Wally was miserable, everyone was going to be
miserable. So let's take a
look real quick, this is our last exercise,
at the
liveware to
life wear aspect.
Any thoughts as to how that was impacted?
And you can put it in the chat, you can answer, or you can do neither of the
above.
Okay.
Neither of the above. Okay. So y'all might be asleep by now.
The conflict wasn't just between Schirra
and Mission Control.
The entire group
presented a united front behind their
leader,
and that was in odds with what Mission Control did,
or what Mission Control recommended.
So, that made the disagreement more significant.
If it was only one rogue astronaut out there,
that may be one thing, but it was the entire crew, and
NASA called it
basically a mutiny.
So, the mutiny made that disagreement between ground control.
It seems like everything that ground control wanted them to do from that point on,
they refused to do, including putting on their helmets, which is a safety
measure on the way down.
Liveware environment.
All three astronauts were miserable
due to a common cold. It wasn't the flu or
anything like that. It was just a common cold.
But the environment's responsible for
that because the free-fall environment, like we talked about earlier,
prevented
normal sinus
drainage. So that would be something due to the
free-fall environment.
And then
liveware, and this is just my opinion, there's really
no right or wrong answer to this, I'm just pointing out some things that I
notice. The liveware software, remember, that includes
procedures.
The planned timeline did not account for anyone getting sick.
So that's why they threw out some of the experiments. They're just like, "I'm sick.
I'm not going to do it today.
You're working me 12 hours a day while I'm sick, so these experiments have
got to go."
So didn't account for contingencies, basically, the
planning.
So it resulted in some positive changes, and there have
been astronauts who were in quarantine
and came down with something, or it was already in them, their
system, and they came down with it, and they had to be removed from
flights after this occurred.
So, any
comments or additions to that,
just put it in the chat.
The Challenger was another example.
I'm not going to explain how the Shell model
applies to this, but you can think about some of these
examples. The Challenger, there were ethical issues, of
course, and procedural issues.
They overrode some of the engineers' recommendations to
not launch, and there were
hardware issues with the O-rings, and
you can put together a complete story.
But notice that none of these have a single cause.
This is a way to narrow down what all the contributing
factors were that led to the disaster.
Apollo 13, there's a lot of lessons learned from using
the Shell model from that. And then, of course, Columbia.
Another one is the Progress-Mir collision, and I'll let
y'all watch this on your own, in
1997.
But there were several failures in
liveware leadership,
procedures, and hardware
that
affected this mission and nearly lost the
lives of its crew members. Fascinating story.
So,
when you put it all together, the bottom line is that about 70% to
80% of all accidents are due
to human error
or human behavior
Okay. So, in summary,
we've covered the
bioastronautics. A lot of topics on bioastronautics.
The main things you should get out of this are
the
NASA roadmap that I introduced you to and the Shell Model,
although there were a lot of other points here that you'll answer in your homework.
You might have to do a little
research there. So this
week, our overall goal was to answer the question: how do we keep astronauts
alive and performing at their best?
Next week, we'll ask the question: how do we keep the spacecraft
itself alive?
Because in space, both humans and machines must survive
the environment. So next week, we're going to talk about the
plasma environment,
and that will include both itself,
definitions,
and how we design spacecraft to survive it.
And also note next week
is
the midterm.
So what I would like you all to do, and I will post a
note on Canvas to this effect.
I really have no way of handling it other than setting up a time with
each of you to administer the exam on a time
basis. It has been
recommended to me. I used to just give it to students
and say, "Okay, you've got 75 minutes to complete it." But it has
been recommended to me by other students and management
above me that that could possibly
encourage cheating, which I disagree with.
I think you all are all adults and would be honorable,
but
I've heard from other students that that doesn't always happen, even at the
graduate level. So on the midterm, email me
with your preferred time.
I will post an announcement for this.
And that would be a...
Whoops, that's not the way you spell preferred.
To
take it.
I will email it to you, and you will have
80 minutes. I'll give you 80 minutes to download it and upload it back up.
You will have 80 minutes to return it to me.
So I would like to have those done
before next class meeting.
No, I'm sorry. Not next class meeting, but the class meeting after that.
Okay.
So that is all I have for tonight.
Are there any questions or comments?
And if not, I will see everyone
on
next Thursday or via video.
Thanks, Rachel.
No other questions from me. Thank you so much for the
lecture.
Thank you, Jordan.
Yep.
Thank you, Ron.
Signing off.